<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ipq-200304--0400">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>EU:s asylprocedurdirektiv samt skyddsgrundsdirektivet</title>
        <author>Fridolin, Gustav (mp)</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SWERIK PROJECT</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>EU:s asylprocedurdirektiv samt skyddsgrundsdirektivet till statsrådet Barbro Holmberg om EU:s asylprocedurdirektiv samt skyddsgrundsdirektivet</title>
          <idno type="rdwebb">GR10400</idno>
          <ref type="dokument_url_text">http://data.riksdagen.se/dokument/GR10400/text</ref>
          <ref type="dokument_url_html">http://data.riksdagen.se/dokument/GR10400</ref>
          <ref type="dokumentstatus_url_xml">http://data.riksdagen.se/dokumentstatus/GR10400</ref>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <particDesc>
        <listPerson>
          <person gender="man">
            <idno>i-9CH1KbWwyrj8DRqAQB3Fza</idno>
            <persName>Gustav Fridolin</persName>
            <state ref="unknown" type="partyAffiliation">
              <desc>MP</desc>
            </state>
          </person>
          <person gender="woman">
            <idno>i-8NR1Z8tejozuay7fUnQPDP</idno>
            <persName>Barbro Holmberg</persName>
            <state ref="unknown" type="partyAffiliation">
              <desc>S</desc>
            </state>
          </person>
          <person gender="woman">
            <idno>i-8NR1Z8tejozuay7fUnQPDP</idno>
            <persName>Barbro Holmberg</persName>
            <state ref="unknown" type="partyAffiliation">
              <desc>S</desc>
            </state>
          </person>
        </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent" xml:id="i-KvKCxvtbB2ezEEn58HvJzK" corresp="i-9CH1KbWwyrj8DRqAQB3Fza">
          <date when="2004-03-31"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received" xml:id="i-VoCRa19NHkqnaHXp6jGYng">
          <date when="2004-03-31"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="answered" xml:id="i-P2KM4SnRJg1qdVCH2K8z3c">
          <date when="2004-04-20"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received" xml:id="i-XiCuoZnQUYKbBeBo4eFjTn" corresp="i-8NR1Z8tejozuay7fUnQPDP">
          <date when="2004-03-31"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="answered" xml:id="i-29THpb8tG5jZNUMsex11nt" corresp="i-8NR1Z8tejozuay7fUnQPDP">
          <date when="2004-04-20"/>
        </correspAction>
        <correspContext corresp="i-29THpb8tG5jZNUMsex11nt">
          <ref type="record" target="prot-200304--098">Riksdagens protokoll 2003/04:98 Tisdagen den 20 april</ref>
          <ref type="recordSection" target="unsetDivId">15 § Svar på interpellation 2003/04:400 om EU:s asylprocedurdirektiv samt skyddsgrundsdirektivet</ref>
        </correspContext>
      </correspDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="ipqHeader">
        <div type="ipqTitle">
          <p xml:id="i-KXSKEh2cncyLeYNt5znW5u">
            Interpellation 2003/04:400 av Gustav Fridolin (mp) till statsrådet
            Barbro Holmberg om EU:s asylprocedurdirektiv samt skyddsgrundsdirektivet
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="ipqSubmissionInfo">
          <p xml:id="i-9h1eGAPgwKRPoSKn7o35uq">
            den 31 mars
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="ipqBody">
        <div type="ipContext">
          <p xml:id="i-2DViM3F7bbiAjZnQVqX2k6">
            EU har under en längre tid sökt enas om två direktiv rörande
            unionens hantering av asylsökande, dels direktivet om "miniminormer
            för medlemsstaternas förfaranden för att bevilja eller återkalla
            flyktingstatus" (känt som asylprocedurdirektivet) och dels direktivet
            om "miniminormer för när tredjelandsmedborgare och statslösa personer
            ska betraktas som flyktingar eller som personer som av andra skäl
            behöver internationellt skydd samt om dessa personers rättsliga
            ställning" (skyddsgrundsdirektivet). Båda direktiven, men främst
            asylprocedurdirektivet, har flera gånger blivit hårt kritiserade
            av olika aktörer på asylområdet. FN:s flyktingorgan UNHCR kritiserade
            redan i november förra året direktiven och ifrågasatte dess förenlighet
            med internationell rätt. Grundsatserna i kritiken var en rädsla
            för att de föreslagna direktiven skulle skapa en erosion i hela
            det globala asylsystemet och att framtida flyktingars liv sattes
            i fara. Inför ministerrådet den 30 mars ställdes frågan till statsrådet
            Barbro Holmberg om hon gjorde bedömningen att UNHCR:s kritik kvarstod
            inför detta möte. Svaret var undvikande och det är troligt att
            nämnden fick intrycket av att statsrådets bedömning var att man
            i huvudsak rättat till de brister UNHCR pekat på.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-SfNA7rbWBMo3bVcUHMZ1UM">
            Det kom dock att visa sig att så inte var fallet. I ett uttalande
            inför ministerrådet den 30 mars upprepade och förstärkte FN:s
            flyktingkommissarie Ruud Lubbers sin kritik (uttalandet hämtat
            från UNHCR:s hemsida på Internet bifogas). Dessutom tillskrev
            tio organisationer med bred erfarenhet på området, däribland Amnesty
            International, Caritas Europa, Human Rights Watch, Kyrkornas flyktingkommission,
            Internationella organisationen för homosexuellas rättigheter,
            Läkare utan Gränser och Rädda Barnen, rådet och kommissionen med
            önskan om att förkasta asylprocedurdirektivet (också detta brev
            bifogas, hämtat från Amnesty Internationals hemsida). Organisationerna
            skriver bland annat att man med bestörtning åser att huvuddelarna
            i asylprocedurdirektivet handlar om att utestänga asylsökande
            från möjligheten att över huvud taget få en asylprocedur. Frivilligorganisationerna
            pekar också på det faktum att miniminormer ofta inte blir golv
            för flyktingpolitiken, utan snarare tak där ingen har en humanare
            flyktingpolitik men några kryper under den gemensamma överenskommelsen.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-VBaUkQRRM9ANhhX6YMAvqD">
            Enligt rapporteringen på Utrikesdepartementets hemsida kom rådet
            den 30 mars aldrig att fatta beslut om de berörda direktiven.
            Det innebär att det fortfarande finns möjlighet, och anledning,
            för Sverige och regeringen att i enlighet med den kritik som framförts
            från UNHCR och människorättsorganisationerna sätta stopp för direktiven.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-WktuQrt14auMgGscwKDNjx">
            Jag vill därför fråga statsrådet Barbro Holmberg följande:
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-4Fn47U6wEzhJfG5MxuJdhq">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att agera för att UNHCR:s kritik
            leder till förändringar vad gäller asylprocedurdirektivet?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-3VVbz8mBDS6WKPr4ZuFEsR">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att verka för att asylprocedurdirektivet
            överensstämmer med internationell rätt (så som den uttolkas av
            UNHCR)?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-XuUzXubs7xv1CvMVZQcHTp">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att agera för att människorättsorganisationernas
            kritik leder till förändringar vad gäller asylprocedurdirektivet?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-9V81x9Q81wU2DqKQutb6Sj">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att agera för att UNHCR:s kritik
            leder till förändringar vad gäller skyddsgrundsdirektivet?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-RUQufrQEo2e1eN3Txv5VPZ">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att säkerställa att de diskuterade
            direktiven inte leder till en sänkt ambitionsnivå i det globala
            asylsystemet?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-G3VFQdQugYqi9qarqyw19E">
            På vilket sätt avser statsrådet att säkerställa att miniminormerna
            i dessa direktiv inte blir den gällande flyktingpolitiken i EU,
            utan enskilda länder vidare värnar asylrätten genom en mer human
            asylprövning?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-DQWjsDo3BPMQ4qDs6gxVj7">
            Hur avser statsrådet att garantera att direktiven inte i förlängningen
            leder till en mer restriktiv och mindre human svensk flyktingpolitik
            och asylprövning?
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-TwGvbTuE4BmnqNjX3cxcTH">
            Bilaga 1:UNHCR:s uttalande
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-CMYLyhPvk6epdsmFFNUWiH">
            Lubbers calls for EU asylum laws not to contravene international
            law
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-YBNJKMeiYe5MB82JRp6EoN">
            UN High Commissioner for Refugees Ruud Lubbers on Monday expressed
            concerns about two key pieces of draft European Union legislation,
            warning that several provisions in the current drafts would fall
            short of accepted international legal standards. Lubbers said
            they could lead to an erosion of the global asylum system, jeopardizing
            the lives of future refugees.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-UBLcQ1e4VqQuhu3iv8jGcQ">
            The two draft directives @ the last in a series of five major
            pieces of legislation intended to harmonize EU asylum law @ will
            be discussed by EU Justice and Home Affairs Ministers in Brussels
            on Tuesday. They are supposed to be finalized in time for the
            1 May enlargement of the European Union.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-9EQyeBn2QeKdMT1VqTumf3">
            "The numbers of asylum seekers coming into the EU have dropped
            sharply and are continuing to do so," Lubbers pointed out.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-RpETyAZBb9ZEr5nDMra6Wa">
            "We can improve the management of asylum by focusing on better
            burden-sharing within the EU," he said. "Even more importantly,
            we can keep numbers down by investing greater effort and resources
            in the regions where refugees are coming from. We're already seeing
            some progress in that respect. There is no need to focus so single-mindedly
            on reducing standards and trying to deter or deny protection to
            as many people as possible."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-F9kGUwXL7772iB7C4Bp6wX">
            Lubbers sent a letter last week to the Irish Prime Minister,
            Bertie Ahern, current holder of the EU Presidency, with two detailed
            notes laying out UNHCR's main concerns: one on the draft Qualification
            Directive, which lays down the definition of who qualifies as
            a refugee and who qualifies for subsidiary protection (used for,
            among others, victims of war); and one on the draft Asylum Procedures
            Directive, which lays down how that decision is reached in the
            case of each individual.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-8U1dH2aRA5psF2eMvkaWaj">
            Lubbers initially raised UNHCR's concerns about the direction
            the Procedures Directive was heading in a statement last November.*
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-NaVbqVEVGs3NAYhSsGz53g">
            In its note, UNHCR lays out a range of concerns including the
            proposed application of the so-called "safe third country" concept
            under which asylum seekers may be sent back to another country
            designated as "safe." The agency criticized a "sweeping exemption"
            that would deny certain asylum seekers access to a procedure altogether,
            disregarding the possibility that a country generally considered
            safe "might nonetheless not be safe for particular individuals."
            This would thereby create a real danger of indirect refoulement
            [forced return] of refugees to possible persecution in their home
            country "in contravention of the 1951 Convention and other international
            human rights law instruments."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-WNzZCbdxNZPALJZAwwvza3">
            Connected to this, UNHCR said the criteria for determining the
            "safety" of a third country are "minimalist" and could lead to
            asylum seekers being sent back to countries that do not maintain
            basic human rights standards and where there is no guarantee their
            cases would be fairly and efficiently examined. This "could amount
            to an effective denial of the right to seek asylum under international
            law," UNHCR said.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-Y8tXsLS5aa3rPAxRqoteUD">
            UNHCR also said that draft Articles relating to appeals could
            also lead to violations of international law. As the text stands,
            "the vast majority" of rejected asylum seekers who lodge an appeal
            will not be permitted to remain in the EU until their appeals
            are decided @ despite the fact that in several European countries
            30-60 percent of initial negative decisions are subsequently overturned
            on appeal.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-M51Rjq2bM48fGe8brgK2x1">
            The text contains a list of wide-ranging exceptions to the principle
            that people should be allowed to remain while their appeals are
            being considered @ exceptions "which have no relation to the merits
            of a person's claim, but are based on technical or discretionary
            factors, or the claimant's behaviour." UNHCR's note said. "For
            example, persons may be removed pending appeal simply because
            they have been detained, or because they failed to make an application
            earlier. Such rules can badly prejudice refugees who are traumatized,
            confused or simply not properly informed about the asylum process."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-TDssFXcqRL7MJ8DTKFVRVP">
            "The cumulative effect of these proposed measures is that the
            EU will greatly increase the chances of real refugees being forced
            back to their home countries," Lubbers said on Monday. "It will
            be hard to track, because the forced return may take place via
            a chain of countries, but that does not mean it will not happen.
            Even a single person being sent back to the risk of torture is
            one too many."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-97pYtJzDBQWNX2zyBzoL2j">
            UNHCR also raised a number of major concerns about the current
            draft of the Qualification Directive, including the proposals
            to severely limit the scope of what constitutes "serious harm"
            (and therefore who qualifies as a beneficiary of international
            protection). These could lead to people fleeing a war zone being
            rejected from all forms of international protection.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-6BUyyZZDztDAv788ysrWZ3">
            Lubbers said that some EU States seemed intent on forcing their
            own most restrictive and controversial practices on to the books
            of all 25 future members of the EU. "In some cases," he said on
            Monday, "these practices have not even been passed into their
            own national legislation, or are under domestic legal challenge,
            yet they are pushing them at the EU level."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-K4msYCRfT5RGeZQasPAjqW">
            Lubbers also said if the EU adopted the Directives in their current
            form it would set a negative precedent for other parts of the
            world, where they would be perceived as an effort to shift the
            burden back to developing countries which already host the great
            majority of the world's refugees. "This could have a knock-on
            effect that might weaken the protection of refugees all across
            the world," he said. "Other countries will look at the EU and
            say 'If they can do this, so can we.'
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-C4PUnJcPZsmCQRzFAbaTuy">
            "We need to remember the original intentions of the harmonization
            process, which was to produce a common European asylum system,
            based @ and here I quote the Tampere Conclusions @ 'on the absolute
            respect for the right to seek asylum' and the 'full and inclusive
            application' of the 1951 UN Refugee Convention. We need to revive
            that spirit.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-79gq7ZbrqG4AxsYuDHnn3H">
            "Europe should be proud of its tradition of giving asylum, of
            saving lives," Lubbers added. "The numbers of asylum seekers are
            going down. We're working hard to find solutions and improve conditions
            in regions of origin, and we are seeing the successes of that
            humane policy and its effect on the numbers moving onwards. It
            would be a real pity if Europe, at this point, were to undermine
            the great tradition of protecting real refugees."
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-LZPoQACKTRiLsYSDhDmPxZ">
            Bilaga 2:
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-5K3oAeLjCancm7BuZXbenP">
            Frivilligorganisationernas brev
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-FoiZU3jFgXFmT2sfkGNKrv">
            RE: Call for withdrawal of the Asylum Procedures Directive
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-GzAYjYykTYCUp6xPB2fukK">
            Dear Mr Vitorino,
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-2VrGoya7EniR28H5RCKTKH">
            As you are aware, the European Council on Refugees and Exiles*
            and the undersigning organisations have closely followed the negotiations
            on the Commission's proposal for a Council Directive on minimum
            standards on procedures in Member States for granting and withdrawing
            refugee status throughout the last four years. We have regarded
            this initiative as a key element of European Union attempts to
            set minimum standards for asylum legislation in accordance with
            the Amsterdam Treaty. We have also appreciated the Commission's
            extensive efforts to facilitate an agreement between Member States,
            amid disparate and often inflexible national positions.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-JCPWphMDD5w1PmMYwnFhpm">
            We are aware that negotiations have not been finalised yet. However,
            in the last stage of this lengthy negotiation process, we note
            that the gaps between this draft Directive and international law
            have grown even wider and that the recommendations repeatedly
            issued by the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, Mr
            Ruud Lubbers, and by civil society organisations have not been
            duly taken into account. We note with deep regret that the most
            contentious provisions are all intended to deny asylum seekers
            access to asylum procedures and to facilitate their transfer to
            countries outside the EU. We are concerned about the effect that
            this abdication from international law obligations will have on
            refugee protection within the EU and elsewhere, as well as on
            the EU's credibility in the international refugee and human rights
            debate. We are now unable
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-2xjn4HYS5MGbNLvERqztQv">
            to further regard this initiative as credible and therefore,
            we are compelled to call on you to withdraw this proposal, as
            it remains in breach of the EU's own commitments as set out in
            the Charter of Fundamental Rights, which is to become part of
            the EU Constitution, as well as individual Member States' responsibilities
            under international refugee and human rights law.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-3W8CarSKRnXTszqGzQH6bk">
            This joint letter intends to highlight the main (but not exclusive)
            concerns of our organisations regarding provisions on safe countries
            of origin, safe third countries (including 'super safe third countries'),
            and the appeal system. While the scope of the letter is restricted
            to these key issues, our organisations also deplore the fact that
            the Directive will mostly be reduced to a catalogue of optional
            provisions, leaving critical issues such as detention and the
            right to legal assistance to Member States' discretion.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-VP68jjH9Lph5B1GV6any6w">
            The current proposal foresees the possibility of using the safe
            country of origin concept to restrict access to the regular asylum
            procedure. While the individual may rebut the presumption of safety,
            s/he may be required to do so in an accelerated procedure with
            only limited safeguards and with the burden of proof lying exclusively
            with him/her. Furthermore, the proposal foresees a common list
            of safe countries of origin binding on all Member States, as a
            result of which, Member States will be forced to use this concept.
            In light of recent practice in some Member States, we are very
            concerned that the safe country of origin concept may be implemented
            by Members States in a way which amounts to discrimination among
            refugees in violation of Article 3 of the 1951 Refugee Convention,
            Article 21 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European
            Union and Article 26 of the International Covenant on Civil and
            Political Rights.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-KGzqJarqaHg3edsavQJD2N">
            We are also concerned about the use of the safe third country
            concept in the proposal, which does not conform with Member States'
            obligations under international law. The proposal allows Member
            States to shift responsibility to third countries, regardless
            of whether the applicant has meaningful links with such countries
            and whether durable solutions exist there, including protection
            against refoulement as established by international law and access
            to a fair and efficient asylum procedure resulting in the recognition
            of refugee status. Under international refugee law, the primary
            responsibility for international protection remains with the State
            where the asylum claim is lodged. A transfer of such responsibility
            can only be envisaged where a meaningful link exists between an
            asylum applicant and a third country which makes a transfer reasonable
            and where the third country is determined safe in the individual
            circumstances of the applicant. Moreover, a transfer can only
            take place if the third State gives its consent to admit or readmit
            the asylum applicant and to provide him/her with full access to
            a fair and efficient determination procedure. The burden of proof
            regarding the safety of the third country for the particular applicant
            lies entirely with the country of asylum and the presumption of
            safety must be rebuttable by the applicant. The proposal in its
            current form, however, does not guarantee sufficiently the right
            of the asylum applicant to rebut the presumption of safety, as
            it may even allow Member States to reject the claim without considering
            the particular circumstances of the applicant, and does not contain
            sufficiently strict criteria for the designation of countries
            as safe.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-VHAVA8Bi2uifJfaK5g6z12">
            Furthermore, we are particularly concerned by the exceptional
            application of the safe third country concept to countries in
            the European region, as it appears in the proposal. No country
            can be labelled as a safe third country for all asylum seekers;
            a decision on a country's safety for a particular applicant must
            always be the outcome of an individual examination of the claim,
            as opposed to a general presumption based on country-related criteria.
            The exceptional application of the safe third country concept,
            however, allows Member States to deny access to the procedure
            to all asylum seekers "illegally" arriving from designated countries
            in the European region and strips them of any rights to rebut
            this presumption. Hence, under the current proposal, a border
            guard without knowledge of international refugee law or national
            asylum provisions could be given the sole power to decide on the
            removal of an asylum applicant to a country even before the competent
            authority has had the chance to look into the claim. In practice,
            this would leave the decision-making authority outside any legal
            framework of accountability for their decisions and could result
            in a serious risk that Member States may violate their international
            obligations to guarantee an effective remedy and to protect against
            refoulement, as enshrined in Article 33 of the 1951 Refugee Convention;
            Articles 3 and 13 of the European Convention on Human Rights;
            Article 3 of the Convention Against Torture; Article 7 of the
            International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights; and Articles
            18, 19 and 47 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European
            Union. Given that the proposal does not require that Member States
            obtain agreement from countries under the exceptional application
            of the safe third country concept to process the asylum claim
            before removing the applicant, the implementation of such a concept
            may lead to refugees-in-orbit situations, and to chain-refoulement,
            which are in breach of the European Convention of Human Rights,
            as it has been repeatedly confirmed by the jurisprudence developed
            by its Court .
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-5GcWGJ7sKJ5jXUcR4M5TNm">
            We also believe that the proposal does not contain adequate appeal
            safeguards for asylum seekers. The right to an effective remedy
            before a court or tribunal is embodied in EC law, in Article 47
            of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union and
            in Article 13 of the European Convention on Human Rights. As held
            by the European Court of Human Rights, it implies the right to
            remain in the territory of the Member State until a final decision
            on the application has been taken. Thus, the right of asylum applicants
            to remain pending a final decision on their cases is essential
            for Member States to comply with their non-refoulement obligations
            and international law provisions related to the right to an effective
            remedy. The proposal, however, does not contain an explicit right
            of all asylum seekers to remain or request for leave to remain
            in the asylum country.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="i-VDqYmw78raHmZcK95ZpaiX">
            In light of the above and as organisations committed to promoting
            international law and fundamental humanitarian values, we find
            the proposal on asylum procedures, in its current form, unacceptable
            as a legal basis for minimum standards in the European Union.
            Therefore, we are forced to call upon the Commission to withdraw
            its proposal for a Council Directive on minimum standards on procedures
            in Member States for granting and withdrawing refugee status.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
